Finding Aid for Thomas Yoder papers, 1967-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas Yoder papers
1967-1991
Yoder, Thomas.
89464 Aa 2
Former member of the Word of God, Ann Arbor, Michigan, Catholic Pentecostal community. Reports, meeting materials, evaluations of the community's leadership, prophecies, printed materials, audiotapes of meetings, and photographs.
11 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Thomas Yoder papers (donor no. 5979 ) came to the library in several accessions beginning in 1977. The collection is on deposit.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Word of God, an Ann Arbor (primarily Catholic) Pentecostal community, traces its beginnings to a small group of individuals who began to pray together regularly in November 1968. Thomas Yoder began to pray with this group in January 1968 and he quickly became an active member of the community. Yoder was very concerned with preserving the history of the group, and became the unofficial historian of the organization.
As time passed, Yoder became increasingly critical of the community's leadership. Eventually, this disagreement with the leadership, and his attempts to carry the dispute outside of the community itself, led to an understanding between Yoder and the leadership that he should terminate his public commitment to the organization. This occurred in November 1976.
The collection consists of materials accumulated by Thomas Yoder and relating to the Word of God community. The collection consists mainly of paper files, sound recordings, and videotapes.
Subjects:
Catholic Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.MichiganAnn Arbor.; Pentecostalism.; Word of God (Religious community); Yoder, Thomas.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Word of God (Religious community)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Collected materials regarding Word of God Community
  The paper files (Collected materials regarding Word of God Community) have been arranged alphabetically by topic and include papers generated by the community itself or its members. Some of the files warrant special mention. As the Word of God community (at least during the period covered by these records) was governed by Coordinators, the Coordinator's notebooks are a valuable source of information regarding the workings of the community. These notebooks include meeting materials, decisions of the coordinators, and outlines and current policies adopted by the coordinators.
  Another excellent source is the "Word of God Archives Documents Book." This volume of documents, now in file folders and numbered, was probably used by Roberta Keene in her thesis "Formal Organization and Charisma in a Catholic Pentecostal Community" (1974). Documents in these files include summary of meetings, planning documents, reports, various statements, and memoranda.
  The Fall Conference files relate to the annual weekend gathering of the entire community. Its purpose is to allow the members to express their collective will. General Community Gatherings referred to in the files are prayer meetings held for the entire community. District Gatherings are prayer meetings of Word of God members living in a specific geographic area. Prophecies were generally given by Word of God members at prayer meetings. Within the community they were usually regarded as being divinely inspired. In recording these prophecies, Yoder relied upon the notes of others, his own notes, and audio tape recordings to reconstitute the prophecies.
  Other files include the Word of God newsletter, Community Bulletin, files relating to the Community's relationship with churches and with associated groups, such as Catholic Charismatic Renewal and the Sword of the Spirit.
  - Background / Informational (Box 1)
    - Articles, letters to the editor, etc. relating to Word of God, 1977-1987 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous articles and clippings, 1970-1988 (Box 1)
    - Articles: Acts Magazine article, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Clippings (photocopies), 1973-1990; undated (Box 1)
  - Calendar, September 1971-December 1972 (Box 1)
  - Catholic Charismatic Prayer Groups, directory, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Catholic Charismatic Renewal, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Charismatic Renewal Services catalogs, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Charismatic Renewal, Materials Relating to
    - Antioch weekend manual, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Bibliography (various), undated (Box 1)
    - Campus Crusade for Christ Literature, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
    - Covenants, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
    - Statements About Charismatic Renewal, 1967-1975 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles National Catholic Reporter, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Articles Southeastern Michigan, 1969-1977 (Box 1)
    - Printed Matter, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1963-1978 (Box 1)
  - Child Care, 1973-1987; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Community Bulletin (newsletter)
    - 1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Community Organization Chart, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Conferences, workshops, etc.
    - General, 1968-1973 (Box 2)
    - National Conferences (Charismatic Renewal), 1970-1981 (Box 2)
    - Catholic Charismatic Renewal Conferences, 1971; 1977 (Box 2)
    - University of Steubenville, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Conference of Communities 1976, and Conference People of Praise 1975, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Coordinator's Notebook
    - Coordinator Meetings, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
    - Decisions of the Coordinators, August 1975 (Box 2)
    - Decisions of the Coordinators, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Coordinator's Meeting Notes, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Coordinator's Meeting Notes, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Courses, 1969-1974 (Box 2)
  - Course: "Living as Christians in Groups", undated (Box 2)
  - Covenant: Comments on the Covenant of a Brotherhood, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Discipleship Dispute, circa 1975 (Box 2)
  - Duin (Julia) book chapter "Living Single ...", 1987 (Box 2)
  - Educational Programs
    - Community Weekend Manual, 1972; 1976 (Box 2)
    - Fruits of the Spirit, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - Living in Christian Community, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Life in the Spirit, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Married Couples, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1977 (Box 2)
  - Fall Conference
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971 (Box 2)
    - 1972, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Father Charles Irvin's Editorials and Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Financial Records and Articles of Incorporation, 1971-1978 (Box 2)
  - Financial Reports
    - 1971-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Finances, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
  - FIRE -- Philippines, undated (Box 2)
  - FIRE and Ralph Martin, 1984-1987 (Box 2)
  - FIRE miscellaneous, 1986; 1989 undated (Box 2)
  - Fireside Cooperative, 1977 (Box 2)
  - General Community Gatherings, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Guest House Register and Information, 1968-1974 (Box 2)
  - Handmaids, Requests for, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Hispanic Missions, 1980-1987 (Box 2)
  - Homosexuality -- Desert Stream, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Human Life Center1987-1988, undated (Box 2)
  - ICO Newsletter, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Information Survey (about individuals, perhaps intended for directory), 1983; 1987 (Box 3)
  - Interviews, testimonies, letters about WOG, 1975-1978 (Box 3)
  - Lamb of God (bulletins), 1988 (Box 3)
  - Leadership and Membership Directories; Dictionary of Abbreviations, 1964-1980 (Box 3)
  - Manuals
    - Leader's Manual: Lord, Teach Us to Pray, undated (Box 3)
    - WOG receptionist's manual, 1990 undated (Box 3)
    - WOG assistant administrator's manual, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - District secretary's manual, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Martin, Ralph
    - General, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Draft: "Face to Face With God", 1987 (Box 3)
  - Mid-west Regional Conference, 1975 (Box 3)
  - "Movement" literature, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Names, 1980-1987; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - National Service Committee (NSC) (Box 3)
  - New Covenant, 1983-1988 (Box 3)
  - Northwest District, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
  - Other Communities and Groups
    - Lamb of God Community (Baltimore, MD), 1984-1987 (Box 3)
    - People of Hope (Newark, NJ), 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - Bread of Life Community (Akron, OH), 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - Christ the King Association, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Covenant Presbyterian, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Emmaus Fellowship, 1984-1988; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Lutheran Fellowship of the Word of God, 1982-1987 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Christian Association, 1983-1987 (Box 3)
    - Family Life Services, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Puebla Institute, 1984-1987 (Box 3)
    - Servants of God's Love (covenant of), undated (Box 3)
    - University Christian Outreach, 1984-1988 (Box 3)
    - Other Organizations (misc.), 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Outreach Programs, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Pastoral Newsletter (Catholic Charismatic Renewal), 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Pastoral Renewal
    - Newsletters, 1978-1990 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1988; undated (Box 3)
    - Printed & Miscellaneous, 1983-1990 (Box 3)
  - Personal Testimonials and Membership Information Requests, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Prayer Meeting card file, including names, prayer requests, church affiliation, etc., 1969 (Box 3)
    (photocopies of index cards)
  - Prayer meeting: photocopies of photographs of Prayer Meeting, handing out of Mantles and Veils, February 1976 (Box 3)
  - Prophecies (Box 4)
    - 1967-1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972-1977 (Box 4)
    - Originals, 1967-1972 (Box 4)
  - Public Commitment, circa 1970-1975 (Box 4)
  - Report: "Report on the Catholic Pentecostal Communities in Greater Detroit", 1970 (Box 4)
  - Report: "A Report on 'The Word of God', A Charismatic Community in Ann Arbor" September 1971 (includes 1972 supplement) (Box 4)
  - St. John Seminary, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - St. Mary's Chapel (relations with WOG), 1968-1976 (Box 4)
  - Schwager, Don: "Servants of Jesus of Christ", 1985 (Box 4)
  - Servant Books, publications by, 1985 undated (Box 4)
  - Servant Ministries, 1981-1988; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Servant Ministries newsletters, 1985-1988 (Box 4)
  - Servants of the Word (The Brotherhood), 1984-1988 (Box 4)
  - Songs of the Word of God, undated (Box 4)
  - Sword of the Spirit (Ann Arbor, MI)
    - Constitution and policy documents, 1977-1989 (Box 5)
    - Policy and Structure, 1983-1987 (Box 5)
    - Training, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Training Course, 1981-1982; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Weddings, 1970-1975 (Box 5)
  - Witnessing, 1968-1981 (Box 5)
  - Word of God Archives Documents Book
    - Contents List 1-150, 1966-1971 (Box 5)
    - Documents No. 1-25, 1964-1969 (Box 5)
    - Documents No. 26-50, 1968-1969 (Box 5)
    - Documents No. 51-100, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Documents No. 101-150, 1970-1972 (Box 5)
    - Documents, 1968-1973 (Box 5)
    - Documents, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Documents, January-June 1976 (Box 5)
    - Documents, July-December 1976 (Box 5)
    - Documents, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Word of God (Box 6)
    - Guest Policies, 1983-1986 (Box 6)
    - Youth activities, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
    - Teachings from Word of God Courses, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Messages Given at Word of God "Gatherings", 1970-1983 (Box 6)
    - Letters and statements critical of Word of God leadership, 1975-1985 (Box 6)
  - Word of God Miscellaneous informational material, 1972 undated (Box 6)
  - Word of God, thesis about: Keane, Roberta Catherine, "Formal Organization and Charisma in a Catholic Pentecostal Community" Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Michigan, 1974 (Box 6)
    (photocopy taken from microfilm)
  - Yoder, Tom, Materials from and Regarding, 1971-1978 (Box 6)
  - Ypsilanti District, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and other papers (arranged chronologically)
    - Undated, 1967-1990; 21 folders (Box 6)
- Sound Recordings
  The Sound Recordings series consists of reel to reel and cassette audiotape recordings. Included were tapes of community anniversary celebrations, the Fall Conference, General Community Gatherings, various educational programs and inter-community conferences.
  - Cassettes
    - Recordings of conference talks and prayer meetings, 1969-1972; 103 audiocassettes in 8 card file boxes (Box 7)
    - Recordings of conference talks and prayer meetings, 1969-1972; 37 audiocassettes in 1 card file box (Box 8)
  - Reel-to-reel tapes
    - Notre Dame Conference, Prophecies, 1972; 5 in. (Box 8)
    - 7 inch, various speeds
      - Community Weekend, September 1970; 2 tapes (Box 8)
      - Prayer meeting talk, Ralph Martin "It Just Doesn't Fit", January 21, 1971 (Box 8)
      - Saturday talk at Fall Conference of Word of God, September 9, 1972; 3 3/4 ips (Box 8)
      - Sunday talk at Fall Conference of Word of God, September 10, 1972 (Box 8)
      - 5th Anniversary celebration, November 22, 1972; 49:24 min.; 7 1/2 ips; 2 track (Box 8)
      - 6th anniversary celebration, October 1973 (Box 8)
        (copy from cassette)
      - CPF, Phil O'Mara, 1974 (Box 8)
      - G.C.C. "Criticism", July 13, 1975 (Box 8)
      - Ralph Martin, August 22, 1976 (Box 8)
      - Fall Word of God Conference, 1976; 2 tapes (Box 8)
      - Interview with Phil O'Mara, February 1977 (Box 8)
      - Music for Prayer Meetings, 3 3/4 ips (Box 8)
    - 10 inch various speeds (Box 9)
      - 1978 Community Conference (Saturday Morning Session) -- "Being a People of Faith" Part I, Bruce Yocum speaker, June 3, 1978 (Box 9)
      - International Conference (Dublin), 1978; 90 min.; 10 in.; 7 1/2 ips; 1/2 track
        - Evangelization I, speakers: Ranaghan, Ferry, Hume, Parmentier, 10 in.; 3 3/4 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
        - Evangelization II, speakers: Ranaghan, Talavera, Emmanuel Cmty., 10 in.; 3 3/4 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
      - International Missionary Conference (Dublin), 1978
        - Basic Christian Communities, speakers; Kevin O'Boyle, Guitterez, 10 in.; 3 3/4 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
      - Steubenville Leaders Conference, 1978
        - Saturday Morning Session, speakers: Shields, Brees (Box 9)
      - "Healing Hurts from God" speaker Fr. Linn, 1978; 10 in.; 7 1/2 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
      - "Gathering a People" speaker Judy Tidings, 1978; 10 in.; 7 1/2 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
      - Wednesday morning conference speakers Father Bertoluchi, Father Scanlon, Bobbie Cauner, 1977; 10 in.; 7 1/2 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
      - Tuesday morning, "Seeking Vision for Local Church", speaker Father Scanlon, 1979; 10 in.; 7 1/2 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
      - General Community Gathering, December 12, 1977; 10 in.; 3 3/4 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
      - "Love and sexuality", 10 in.; 7 1/2 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
      - Anniversary celebration GCG and piano at dinner, December 11, 1977; 10 in.; 3 3/4 ips; 1/2 track (Box 9)
        ("poor playing")
      - Father Herb Schneider Conference, 10 in.; 7 1/2 ips; 1/2 track
        - July 3, 1984 (Box 10)
        - July 5, 1984 (Box 10)
        - July 6, 1984 (Box 10)
        - July 7, 1984 (Box 10)
        - July 9, 1984 (Box 10)
        - July 10, 1984, 2 reels (Box 10)
        - July 11, 1984 (Box 10)
        - July 12, 1984 (Box 10)
        - July 13, 1984 (Box 10)
        - July 14, 1984 (Box 10)
      - Unidentified, 11 reels (Box 11)
- Videotapes
  The videotapes are of a four part series given by Ralph Martin on the holiness of God.
  - Holiness messages, Ralph Martin, 1986; vhs videotapes
    - The Holiness of God (Box 11)
    - Our Encounter with the Holiness of God (Box 11)
    - Growth in Holiness (Box 11)
    - Holiness and Suffering (Box 11)
- Microfilm
  - Various records, 2 reels (Box 11)
    (These microfilm reels were made in 1978 when Thomas Yoder requested that his papers be returned to him; he allowed the library to make a microfilm copy of the files; in 1982 he returned the papers to the library; this microfilm is a copy of the files now dispersed throughout boxes 1-6)